Guide to the Maurice Baring Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maurice Baring collection
1891-1939
GEN MSS 322
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.8
(2 boxes)
Includes letters from Baring to Eugénie Strong, 1900-1939, and a carbon of one letter from Strong to Baring, 1925; corrected typescript of "The Coat Without Seam"; corrected proofs of "The Song of the Nameless", with manuscript poem; corrected typescript of "Passages from Three Notebooks"; manuscript volume labeled: "French Parodies and Russian Exercises"; manuscript volume of various poems labeled "Sonnets and Lyrics"; and corrected typescript and manuscript of "A Luncheon Party".
Baring, Maurice, 1874-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded in series level notes. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Maurice Baring, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to October 1997 have been organized into four series: Series I, Gift of L. D. C. (Lady Diana Duff Cooper), Series II, Gift of Elizabeth Hudson, Series III, Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel, and Series IV, Additional Materials, which consists of papers acquired from various sources.
Poetry; The Coat Without Seam; The Song of the Nameless; Baring, Maurice, 1874-1945; Strong, Eugénie, 1860-1943
- Gift of L. D. C., 1891-1929; Series I; 0.4' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of L. D. C., 1962
  - 2 ALS to [Edmund Gosse], London and White's, [1904], 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The 1928 letter removed from his A Year in Russia, London [1907]. The 1904 letter removed from his Hildesheim, Paris, 1899
  - The Coat Without Seam, corrected typescript, [1929?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "French Parodies and Russian Exercises," manuscript volume, [1899] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Acc #: 621002-a
  - "Passages from Three Notebooks," typescript with corrections, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Acc #: 621002-b
  - "Retrospect in Silver and Russet," manuscript poem in an unidentified hand, [1894] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "With apologies to Mr. Edmund Gosse." Note on p. 2: This parody of me was written by Maurice Baring in 1894, E.G.
  - "Sonnets and Lyrics," manuscript volume, 1891-92 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Acc #: 621002-c
- Gift of Elizabeth Hudson, 1891-1939; Series II; 0.13' (1/3 box)
  Gift of Elizabeth Hudson, 1970-1976
  - ALS to James Bain, London, 1931 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Removed from his The Last Cruise of H.M.S. Tiger, 1931. Accompanied by a note from James Bain to John M. Cameron
  - TL to Edith Somerville, Rottingdean, 1939 Feb 16 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Removed from the library of Edith Somerville
  - Cat's Cradle, typescript of a screen adaptation by A. Mauclair, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    A note on the front cover signed EH [Elizabeth Hudson] explains the circumstances of this adaptation
  - "Damosel Blanche," manuscript with revisions, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Bound manuscript of several poems, title derived from spine
    Acc #: 960725-c
  - "Ivo Grenfell," corrected proof signed by the author, 1926 Oct 8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    London, privately printed, 1927. Accompanied by a letter from Baring to Mr. Evans, 13 Apr 1927, sending him the corrected proof
  - "My soul is like a cigarette," autograph manuscript poem, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Oh! mon chat," autograph manuscript poem, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Sonnet. Written to a young lady," proof of a poem, signed by Baring, [1910?] (Box 2, Folder 14)
    On conjugate leaf: "East and West," poem signed "H. Belloc"; the signature and 3 manuscript lines apparently in the hand of Maurice Baring. Pencil note on verso: "From the North Street Press. May. 1910."
- Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel, 1891-1939; Series III; 0.13' (1/3 box)
  Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel, 1970-1976
  - ALS to H. Buxton Forman, Eton, 1891 Nov 27 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    On p. 7 is a fair copy (signed with initials) of his poem "To Shelley"
  - 28 ALS, 11 TL or TLS, and 3 telegrams to Eugénie Strong, 1900-1939 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    The letter of 24 April 1925 encloses a prayer. Accompanied by a carbon of a letter from Eugénie Strong to Maurice Baring, 17 November 1925
  - Slipcase for letters to Eugénie Strong, with Halsted B. VanderPoel's initials and insignia stamped on spine (Box 2, Folder 18a)
  - "The Song of the Nameless," corrected proofs with manuscript poem, ca. 1907 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Additional Materials, 1923-1939; Series IV; 0.13' (1/3 box)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, London, 1923 Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Removed from [Baring, Hon. Maurice] I.M.H., by C. London, 1923
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Hyères, 1933 Feb 8 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Removed from his Pastels and Other Rhymes, 1891
  - ALS (with initials) to an unidentified recipient, Gibraltar, 1934 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified TLS to "My dear Friend", 1939 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "A Luncheon Party," autograph manuscript and typescript, both with corrections (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Acc #: 810316-a